Guide to the Thomas G. Masaryk Papers, 1918-1938 SC.1983.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thomas G. Masaryk Papers
1918-1938
1918-1919
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Masaryk, T. G. (Tomáš Garrigue)
SC.1983.01
3 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Thomas Masaryk was an Austro-Hungarian and Czechoslovak politician, philosopher, and an icon of Czechoslovak independence by becoming the founder and first elected President of Czechoslovakia in 1918. The collection includes mostly unpublished drafts of Masryk's letters and memoranda, interviews, and articles and drafts of later published writings. The date range of the collection (1918-1919) is significant as it was during this period that Masaryk's ultimate goal of Czechoslovak sovereignty came to fruition.
Biography
Thomas Masaryk was born on March 7, 1850, in the former Austro-Hungarian Empire, into a working-class family of Slovak, Moravian, and Slavic decent. This ethnic decent later informed and motivated much of his life's work. After studying philosophy in Brno, Leipzig, and Vienna, Masaryk was named Professor of Philosophy at the University of Prague in 1882. As part of his dedication to Czech civilization, Masaryk began a magazine concentrated on Czech culture and science. Masaryk was also elected to the Austrian parliament, first, as a member of the Young Czech Party, and then again as a member of the Realist Party.
With the eruption of World War I in 1914, Masaryk found that the best way to attain his ultimate ideal of Czechoslovak independence from Austria-Hungary was through self-imposed exile. Between late 1914 and early 1918, Masaryk made his way across Europe and Asia to the United States -– promoting, organizing, and establishing the Czechoslovak cause along the way. His travels did much in the way of establishing the Czechoslovak Legions, which were military units designed to aid the Allied cause in Russia. The connections established by Masaryk during this period also provided the Allies with valuable intelligence and counter-intelligence information.
Named president of the provisional Czechoslovak government by the Allies, after the dissolution of the Austro-Hungarian Empire at the close of World War I, Masaryk was elected the president of a sovereign Czechoslovak Republic in 1918. He was reelected in 1920, 1927, and 1934. Due to ailing health, he resigned as president in 1935, with Dr. Edvard Benes taking the office. Two years later, on September 14, 1937, Thomas Masaryk died of natural causes.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Czechoslovak Nationality Room Committee of the University of Pittsburgh on March 6, 1983.
Previous Citation
Thomas G. Masaryk Papers, 1918-1919, SC.1983.01, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Existence and Location of Originals
Photocopies in this collection are derived from originals located at the National Archives State Department Files in Washington, D.C., the Richard T. Crane Papers at the Georgetown University Library, and the Woodrow Wilson Papers at the Library of Congress.
Arrangement
The papers are stored in two document boxes and are divided into eleven series:
Series I. Czechoslovak Legion in Siberia
Series II. Letters to Woodrow Wilson and Robert Lansing
Series III. Articles and Interview
Series IV. The Poles: Tesin and Orava
Series V. Hungarian Invasion of Slovakia, Spring of 1919
Series VI. Messages to Benes in Paris
Series VII. Record of Discussion with General Smuts – April 7, 1919
Series VIII. Draft of First Message to Parliament
Series IX. First Outline of Nova Europa
Series X. Miscellaneous
Series XI. Czech Periodicals
Scope and Content Notes
The papers in this collection detail Masaryk's work from 1918 to 1919 at the end of the First World War. This work includes the formation of a sovereign, internationally recognized Czechoslovak state, the situation of Czechoslovak troops in the final phases of the war, the state of the Czechoslovak people after the war, and the relations of Czechoslovakia with neighboring former Central Powers (especially Poland and the Austro-Hungarian Empire) in the immediate aftermath of the war. The papers are comprised of notes, interviews, memoranda, letters, drafts, articles, telegrams, and messages.
A later addition to the collection (Series 11) contains nine issues of Czech periodicals featuring articles and images of Masaryk's life and death.
Personal papers; Articles; Telegrams; Notes; Memorandums; Interviews; Correspondence; Presidents -- Czechoslovakia; Czechoslovakia -- Politics and government -- 1918-1938; Czechoslovakia -- Foreign relations -- 1918-1938; World War, 1914-1918; Czechoslovakia -- History -- 1918-1938; Masaryk, T. G. (Tomáš Garrigue)
- Czechoslovak Legion in Siberia, 1918; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series includes telegrams, correspondence, notes, and memoranda regarding the situation of Czechoslovak troops deployed in Russia (most notably Siberia). Masaryk comments on the precarious situation of the Czechoslovak troops, essentially stranded in Siberia due to the withdrawal of Bolshevik Russia from the war and its ensuing compliance with the Germans.
  - Statement of the Czechoslovak Government concerning the Principle of Nonintervention in Russia, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Return of the Siberian Legions to the Homeland, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Telegram to the Czechoslovak Army in Russia, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Confidential Memorandum: "Help of the Allies to the Czechoslovak Army in Russia Necessary", 1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Report of Capt. Hurban Regarding the Chaos in Russia and Siberia – Emendations by Thomas Masaryk, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agreement with Gen. Janin on the Situation in Russia, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Notes on the Memorandum of September 27, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letters to Woodrow Wilson and Robert Lansing, 1918; II.
  These documents, dating from March and November of 1918, consist of English and Czech versions of Masaryk's letters to U.S. President Woodrow Wilson and Secretary of State Robert Lansing. The letters deal with the formation and hopeful U.S. support of a democratic union of mid-European states. The issue of war guilt is also discussed, with the case against the Austrians and Magyars being clearly made. Apprehensions over Polish intentions are also raised.
  - Letter to President Wilson on the Mid-European Union, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter to Secretary Lansing Regarding War Guilt – Dr. Cisar's Transcript with Masaryk's Emendations and Additions, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Articles and Interviews, 1918-1919; III.
  This series is comprised of various articles and interviews featured in such periodicals as The Nation. The content of these articles and interviews surrounds the status of Czechoslovakia following the First World War. Masaryk details the significant historical and political dimensions of the new Czechoslovak state, as well as noting the value of recognition by the United States. He also makes known the plight of the Czechoslovak people in terms of the poverty and starvation they had to contend with. The documents are a mixture of hand-written and typed pages in both English and Czech.
  - The International Status of the Czechoslovak Nation, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Interview with an Unidentified English Journalist, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Article about the Impoverization of Czech Lands by War, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Austrophiles among the Allies, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Response to the Swiss Inquiry concerning the Union of Austria and Germany, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- The Poles: Tesin and Orava, 1919; IV.
  These papers, written during 1919, deal with the Czechoslovakian relationship with Poland. In particular, a defense is made of Czechoslovakia as regards Polish claims of their being "the Prussians among the Slavs." The Interallied Commission is implored not to be swayed by Polish politicking against Czechoslovakia. Documents are in both English and Czech, handwritten and typed.
  - Transcript of Telegram from Mr. Paderewski with Draft of Masaryk's Response, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Masaryk's Letter to Mr. Paderewski, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Masaryk's Letter to Dr. Svatek, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Masaryk's Letter to the Inter-Allied Commission at Tesin, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letter to Premier Kramer regarding Poland, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Mr. Maxa's Report from Warsaw, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Hungarian Invasion of Slovakia, Sping of 1919; V.
  This series contains documents from 1919 which focus on relations with Hungary. All documents, both typed and handwritten, are in Czech.
  - Letter to Dr. Benes, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Notes on Relations with the Government in Budapest, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Concerning the Advancement of our Army into Hungary", 1919 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Messages to Benes in Paris, 1919; VI.
  These documents consist of two forms of Masaryk's correspondence with Dr. Benes – typed and handwritten. The communication dates from March of 1919. Both documents appear in the original Czech.
  - Message to Dr. Benes in Paris: Draft of Letter, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Discussion with General Smuts, April 7, 1919; VII.
  This series features the discussion with General Smuts on April 7, 1919. The document consists of six handwritten pages in Czech.
  - Discussion with General Smuts, April 7, 1919 (8:30-9:40) (Box 1, Folder 25)
- The First Message to Parliament, 1918; VIII.
  Contained in this series is the draft of Masaryk's first message to the parliament of the Czechoslovak Republic. The document consists of twenty-seven handwritten pages, in Czech, dated to December 22, 1918.
  - Draft of the First Message to Parliament, December 22, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- First Outline of Nova Europa, 1918; IX.
  In this first outline of Nova Europa, Masaryk presents his introduction with a topical outline handwritten in Czech, accompanied by an index of subjects, namely nations, written in English.
  - Introduction and Topical Outline, with Index of Subjects, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1918-1919; X.
  These documents are comprised of miscellaneous documents ranging from 1918 to 1919. They include Masaryk's correspondence with Herbert Hoover, communication with his Minister of Defense, and drafts of his wife's correspondence. The documents are both typed and handwritten, and in both English and Czech.
  - Portion of a Letter Drafted to Herbert Hoover, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Draft of a Letter to Col. House, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Masaryk's Draft about Mrs. Masaryk's Appreciation of Greetings Received at Sokol Slet, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Letter to Defense Minister Klofac regarding Military Matters in Rusinia, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Draft of Letter to Defense Minister Klofac regarding Military Matters in Italy, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Czech Periodicals, 1932-1938; XI
  This series constitutes a later addition to the Masaryk Papers. It contains nine issues of Czech periodicals and one Czech magazine clipping with articles and images about President Masaryk,including his death and funeral. The titles include Pestrý týden [Colorful Week], one of the best illustrated magazines that appeared in the first and second Czechoslovak Republic, and Pražský ilustrovaný zpravodaj [Prague Illustrated Reporter], the first Czech magazine focusing on reporting through photography and images, thus initiating a new evolution in the Czech media market.
  - Pestrý týden: "In Memoriam TGM, 19. října 1937", October 1937 (Box 2, Item 1)
  - Pestrý týden, July 1938 (Box 2, Item 2)
  - Pestrý týden, Septmeber 1937 (Box 2, Item 3)
  - Clipping from Unidentified Publication (Box 2, Item 4)
  - Pražský ilustrovaný zpravodaj, 1937 (Box 2, Item 5)
  - Pražský ilustrovaný zpravodaj, 1937 (Box 2, Item 6)
  - Ozvěny domova i světa, 1937 (Box 2, Item 7)
  - Pražský ilustrovaný zpravodaj, 1938 (Box 2, Item 8)
  - Slavnostní list, July 1932 (Box 2, Item 9)
  - Slavnostní list, June 1932 (Box 2, Item 10)